<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>transformer | Shreyansh Singh</title>
    <link>https://shreyansh26.github.io/tags/transformer/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://shreyansh26.github.io/tags/transformer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>transformer</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Shreyansh Singh 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2022 14:57:33 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://shreyansh26.github.io/img/Shreyansh.jpg</url>
      <title>transformer</title>
      <link>https://shreyansh26.github.io/tags/transformer/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ConvNeXt - Adversarial images generation</title>
      <link>https://shreyansh26.github.io/project/convnext-adversarial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 20:40:05 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shreyansh26.github.io/project/convnext-adversarial/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I implemented &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/stanislavfort/status/1481263565998805002?s=20&#34;&gt;Stanislav Fort&amp;rsquo;s project&lt;/a&gt; in Pytorch. The Github repo has a notebook which looks at generating adversarial images to &amp;ldquo;fool&amp;rdquo; the ConvNeXt model&amp;rsquo;s image classification capabilities. ConvNeXt came out earlier this year (2022) from Meta AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FGSM (Fast Gradient Sign Method) is a great algorithm to attack models in a white-box fashion with the goal of misclassification. Noise is added to the input image (not randomly) but in a manner such that the direction is the same as the gradient of the cost function with respect to the data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper Summary #5 - XLNet: Generalized Autoregressive Pretraining for Language Understanding</title>
      <link>https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2021 14:25:04 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper&lt;/strong&gt;: XLNet: Generalized Autoregressive Pretraining for Language Understanding&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Link&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08237.pdf&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1906.08237.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: Zhilin Yang, Zihang Dai, Yiming Yang, Jaime Carbonell, Ruslan Salakhutdinov, Quoc V. Le&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Code&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zihangdai/xlnet&#34;&gt;https://github.com/zihangdai/xlnet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what&#34;&gt;What?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper proposes XLNet, a generalized autoregressive pretraining method that enables learning bidirectional contexts over all permutations of the factorization order and overcomes the limitations of BERT due to the autoregressive formulation of XLNet. XLNet incorporates Transformer-XL as the underlying model. It outperforms BERT in 20 NLP tasks like question answering, natural language inference, sentiment analysis and document ranking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing unsupervised representation learning approaches can be divided into two types - autoregressive language modeling and autoencoding approaches. The autoregressive methods like ELMo and GPT tried to estimate the probability distribution of a text corpus with an autoregressive model. They had a limitation in that they only captured the unidirectional context. BERT aimed to solve this problem by aiming to reconstruct the original data from the corrupted input. So BERT could capture the bidirectional context, but by converting this into a prediction problem, BERT assumed that the predicted tokens are independent of each other. However, that is not the case in natural language where long term dependency is prevalent. Moreover, the use of the [MASK] tokens also created a pretrain-finetune discrepancy as there are no [MASK] tokens available during finetuning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XLNet tries to leverage the best of both worlds. The qualities of XLNet are -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XLNet computes the maximum likelihood of a sequence w.r.t. all possible permutations of the factorization order. So when calculating the expectation, each position learns to capture the context from all positions, hence capturing bidirectional context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XLNet does not rely on data corruption as in BERT and hence does not suffer from the pretrain-finetune discrepancy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;XLNet integrates the novelties from Transformer-XL like recurrence mechanism and relative encoding scheme (explained later as well). This improves the performance of tasks that utilise a longer text sequence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autoregressive language modeling performs pretraining by maximizing the likelihood under the forward autoregressive factorization -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/arobjective.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/arobjective.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; is the given text sequence. h&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x&lt;sub&gt;1:t-1&lt;/sub&gt;) is the context representation produced by the model and &lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;(x) is the embedding of &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denoising autoencoding approach like BERT first constructs a corrupt version &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;(cap) by randomly masking a fraction (15%) of tokens of &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; to a special symbol [MASK]. The masked tokens are denoted by &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;(bar). So, the training objective in the case of BERT becomes -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/aeobjective.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/aeobjective.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; is 1 when &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; is masked. Here H&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt; is a Transformer that maps each token to a sequence of length &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; to hidden vectors [H&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x)&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, H&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x)&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, &amp;hellip;, H&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x)&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In BERT, the conditional probability is taken when the input is masked, denoted using &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;. Hence denoting the independence assumption among the targets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;objective-permutation-language-modeling&#34;&gt;Objective: Permutation Language Modeling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both autoregressive and autoencoding approaches have their benefits over each other. XLNet tries to bring both their advantages into the picture while avoiding their weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XLNet proposes the use of permutation language modeling objective that looks like the general autoregressive language modeling approach but it allows the model to capture bidirectional context as well. Here, the training is performed for each valid autoregressive factorization order (permutations) of the sequence. The model parameters are shared across all the factorization orders, and hence the model learns to capture information from all positions on both sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed permutation language modeling approach is -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/xlnetobjective.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/xlnetobjective.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;em&gt;Z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;T&lt;/sub&gt; is the set of all possible permutations of the length-&lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; index sequence [1, 2, 3&amp;hellip;, T]. &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; and z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;t&lt;/sub&gt; denote the t-th element and the first &lt;em&gt;t-1&lt;/em&gt; elements of the permutation. So, basically the autoregressive formulation is applied for each factorization order z.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this is based on the autoregressive framework, the independence assumption of BERT is no longer present in this case and the pretrain-finetune discrepancy is also not present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* One must note that here the objective does not permute the sequence order. The sequence order remains as it is and the positional encodings correspond to the original sequence itself. Here, the attention mask in Transformers is used to achieve the permutation of the factorization order. This is done because permuting the sequence itself can cause problems as during finetuning, the natural order will always be preserved. The authors do not want to include any other pretrain-finetune discrepancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;architecture-two-stream-self-attention-for-target-aware-representations&#34;&gt;Architecture: Two-Stream Self-Attention for Target-Aware Representations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the Transformer(-XL) directly with the permutation language modeling objective will not work. This is because, say we have two sequences, in which z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;t&lt;/sub&gt; sequence is same but the z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; token is different. And in the current formulation using transformers(-XL) the z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;t&lt;/sub&gt; sequence determines z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; but that would not be correct if we predict the same distribution for both the sequences while they have two different tokens as the target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve this, a re-parameterization of the next-token distribution with the target-position (z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;) is required.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/rexlnetobjective.png&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/rexlnetobjective.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, g&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;i&gt;z&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;) is a new type of representation that takes in the z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; as input as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;two-stream-self-attention&#34;&gt;Two-Stream Self-Attention&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, there is a contradiction here. If we want to predict x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, g&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;i&gt;z&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;) should only use position z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; and not x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; itself. Also, to predict the future tokens x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; with j &amp;gt; t, we need  x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; to provide the full context information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to resolve this, XLNet uses two hidden representations -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content representation h&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;=t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;) abbreviated as h&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, which is similar to the general Transformer hidden state. This encodes both the context and the token x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Query representation g&lt;sub&gt;Θ&lt;/sub&gt;(x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, &lt;i&gt;z&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;) , abbreviated as g&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;, which only has access to the contextual information x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; and the position z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt; but not the contents x&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/arch.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/arch.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above diagram shows the flow of the two streams. The two streams are updated with a set of shared parameters as follows -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/update.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/update.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The update rule of the content representations is exactly the same as the standard self-attention. During finetuning, the query stream can be dropped and the content stream can be used as a normal Transformer(-XL). And in the end, the last-layer query representation g&lt;sub&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;t&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; is used to compute the likelihood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;//downloads.mailchimp.com/js/signup-forms/popup/unique-methods/embed.js&#34; data-dojo-config=&#34;usePlainJson: true, isDebug: false&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;button style=&#34;background-color: #70ab17; color: #1770AB&#34; id=&#34;openpopup&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt; --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;button_cont&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;button id=&#34;openpopup&#34; class=&#34;example_a&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .example_a {
        color: #fff !important;
        text-transform: uppercase;
        text-decoration: none;
        background: #3f51b5;
        padding: 20px;
        border-radius: 5px;
        cursor: pointer;
        display: inline-block;
        border: none;
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }

    .example_a:hover {
        background: #434343;
        letter-spacing: 1px;
        -webkit-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        -moz-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        box-shadow: 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;

function showMailingPopUp() {
    window.dojoRequire([&#34;mojo/signup-forms/Loader&#34;], function(L) { L.start({&#34;baseUrl&#34;:&#34;mc.us4.list-manage.com&#34;,&#34;uuid&#34;:&#34;0b10ac14f50d7f4e7d11cf26a&#34;,&#34;lid&#34;:&#34;667a1bb3da&#34;,&#34;uniqueMethods&#34;:true}) })

    document.cookie = &#34;MCPopupClosed=;path=/;expires=Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 UTC&#34;;
}

document.getElementById(&#34;openpopup&#34;).onclick = function() {showMailingPopUp()};

&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;partial-prediction&#34;&gt;Partial Prediction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a given factorization order &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;z&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;,  cutting point &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; is chosen which splits the sequence into two subsequences. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;z&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&amp;lt;=c&lt;/sub&gt; is the non-target subsequence and &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;z&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;&amp;gt;c&lt;/sub&gt; is the target sequence. The objective to maximize the log-likelihood of the target subsequence conditioned on the non-target subsequence is written as -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/partial.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/partial.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hyperparameter &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; is chosen to determine what fraction of the sequence length will be the target sequence. This is done so that sufficient sequence length is present for the model to learn the context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here again, XLNet differs from BERT. Let us consider an example [New, York, is, a city]. If both BERT and XLNet take two tokens [New, York] as the prediction task and so they have to maximize p(New York | is a city). Here BERT and XLNet get the following objectives -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/bertxlnet.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/bertxlnet.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;XLNet considers the dependency in the target subsequence as well i.e., how &amp;ldquo;York&amp;rdquo; depends on &amp;ldquo;New&amp;rdquo; as well. XLNet always learns more dependency pairs given the same target and contains “denser” effective training signals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ideas-from-transformer-xl&#34;&gt;Ideas from Transformer-XL&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transformer-XL introduced the segment recurrence mechanism for caching and reuse of the previous segment knowledge. For a long sequence &lt;strong&gt;s&lt;/strong&gt;, if we take two segments &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;(bar) and &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt; which are permutations of the segment, then the obtained representations from the first segment h(bar)&lt;sup&gt;(m)&lt;/sup&gt; for each layer &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; can be cached and reused for the next segment. This can be written as -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/recur.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/recur.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also since the positional embeddings depend on the actual positions in the original sequence, the above attention update is independent of the previous segment once the hidden representations have been calculated. So the factorization order of the previous segment need not be known. Subsequently, the model learns to utilize the memory over all factorization orders of the last segment. The same is done for the query stream as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;modeling-multiple-segments&#34;&gt;Modeling Multiple Segments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like BERT, XLNet randomly samples two segments (either from the same context or not) and treats the concatenation of two segments as one sequence to perform permutation language modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XLNET introduces Relative Segment Encodings. Unlike BERT which had absolute segment embeddings that were added to the word embedding at each position, here, rather than giving the entire segment an encoding, relative encoding is used between positions to denote whether they belong to the same segment or not.
The segment encoding of the positions is used to compute the attention weight. So, when position &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; attends to &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt;, the segment encoding s&lt;sub&gt;&lt;i&gt;ij&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/sub&gt; is used to compute an attention weight a&lt;sub&gt;ij&lt;/sub&gt; = (q&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; + b)&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt;s&lt;sub&gt;ij&lt;/sub&gt; , where q&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; is the query vector as in a standard attention operation and &lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt; is a learnable head-specific bias vector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relative segment encodings help because -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Inductive bias of the relative encodings improves the generalization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opens up the possibility of finetuning on tasks that have more than two input segments, which is not possible when using absolute segment encodings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two datasets were the same as the ones BERT used i.e., BooksCorpus and English Wikipedia. Furthermore, Giga5, ClueWeb 2012-B and CommonCrawl datasets were also used. SentencePiece tokenization was used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XLNet had the same architecture hyperparameters as BERT-Base and XLNet-Large had the same hyperparameters as BERT-Large. this resulted in similar model size and hence a fair comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;XLNet was trained on 512 TPU v3 chips for 500K steps with an Adam weight decay
optimizer, linear learning rate decay, and a batch size of 8192, which took about 5.5 days. And even after using so much compute and time, the model still underfitted on the data at the end of the training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the recurrence mechanism is introduced, XLNet uses a bidirectional data input pipeline where each of the forward and backward directions takes half of the batch size. The idea of span-based prediction, where first, a sample length &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt; from [1, &amp;hellip;, 5] is chosen and then a consecutive span of &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt; tokens is randomly selected as prediction targets within a context of (&lt;em&gt;KL&lt;/em&gt;) tokens.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comparisonwithbert.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comparisonwithbert.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen above, trained on the same data with an almost identical training recipe,
XLNet outperforms BERT by a sizable margin on all the considered datasets.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp1.PNG&#34; data-caption=&#34;Performance on reading comprehension and document ranking tasks. Comparison with GPT, BERT, RoBERTa and a BERT ensemble&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp1.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Performance on reading comprehension and document ranking tasks. Comparison with GPT, BERT, RoBERTa and a BERT ensemble
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp2.PNG&#34; data-caption=&#34;Performance on question answering tasks - SQuADv1.1 and SQuADv2.0&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp2.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Performance on question answering tasks - SQuADv1.1 and SQuADv2.0
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp3.PNG&#34; data-caption=&#34;Performance on text classification task.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp3.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Performance on text classification task.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;














&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp4.PNG&#34; data-caption=&#34;Performance on natural language understanding tasks - the GLUE benchmark.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/comp4.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Performance on natural language understanding tasks - the GLUE benchmark.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For explicit reasoning tasks like SQuAD and RACE that involve longer context, the performance gain of XLNet is larger. The use of Transformer-XL could be the main reason behind this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For classification tasks that already have abundant supervised examples such as MNLI (&amp;gt;390K), Yelp (&amp;gt;560K) and Amazon (&amp;gt;3M), XLNet still lead to substantial gains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ablation study&lt;/strong&gt; was also performed to understand the importance and effect of introducing each component. The points of the study were -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The effectiveness of the permutation language modeling objective alone, especially compared to the denoising auto-encoding objective used by BERT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The importance of using Transformer-XL as the backbone neural architecture. For this, a DAE + Transformer-XL model was used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The necessity of some implementation details including span-based prediction, the bidirectional input pipeline, and next-sentence prediction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a fair comparison, all models were based on a 12-layer architecture with the same model hyper-parameters as BERT-Base and were trained on only Wikipedia and the BooksCorpus. All results reported are the median of 5 runs.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/ablation.PNG&#34; data-caption=&#34;Performance on natural language understanding tasks - the GLUE benchmark.&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-16_generalized_autoregressive_pretraining_xlnet/images/ablation.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Performance on natural language understanding tasks - the GLUE benchmark.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the table -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transformer-XL and the permutation LM (the basis of XLNet) are big factors in the superior performance of XLNet over BERT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On removing the memory caching mechanism, the performance drops especially for RACE where long context understanding is needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Span-based prediction and bidirectional input pipeline also help in the performance of XLNet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The next-sentence prediction objective does not lead to an improvement. Hence the next-sentence prediction objective is excluded from XLNet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have also released an annotated version of the paper. If you are interested, you can find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shreyansh26/Annotated-ML-Papers/blob/main/XLNet.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all for now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;//downloads.mailchimp.com/js/signup-forms/popup/unique-methods/embed.js&#34; data-dojo-config=&#34;usePlainJson: true, isDebug: false&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;button style=&#34;background-color: #70ab17; color: #1770AB&#34; id=&#34;openpopup&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt; --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;button_cont&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;button id=&#34;openpopup&#34; class=&#34;example_a&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .example_a {
        color: #fff !important;
        text-transform: uppercase;
        text-decoration: none;
        background: #3f51b5;
        padding: 20px;
        border-radius: 5px;
        cursor: pointer;
        display: inline-block;
        border: none;
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }

    .example_a:hover {
        background: #434343;
        letter-spacing: 1px;
        -webkit-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        -moz-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        box-shadow: 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;

function showMailingPopUp() {
    window.dojoRequire([&#34;mojo/signup-forms/Loader&#34;], function(L) { L.start({&#34;baseUrl&#34;:&#34;mc.us4.list-manage.com&#34;,&#34;uuid&#34;:&#34;0b10ac14f50d7f4e7d11cf26a&#34;,&#34;lid&#34;:&#34;667a1bb3da&#34;,&#34;uniqueMethods&#34;:true}) })

    document.cookie = &#34;MCPopupClosed=;path=/;expires=Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 UTC&#34;;
}

document.getElementById(&#34;openpopup&#34;).onclick = function() {showMailingPopUp()};

&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script data-name=&#34;BMC-Widget&#34; data-cfasync=&#34;false&#34; src=&#34;https://cdnjs.buymeacoffee.com/1.0.0/widget.prod.min.js&#34; data-id=&#34;shreyanshsingh&#34; data-description=&#34;Support me on Buy me a coffee!&#34; data-message=&#34;&#34; data-color=&#34;#FF5F5F&#34; data-position=&#34;Right&#34; data-x_margin=&#34;18&#34; data-y_margin=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/shreyansh_26&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shreyansh26&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; or connect on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/shreyansh26/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper Summary #4 - BERT: Pre-training of Deep Bidirectional Transformers for Language Understanding</title>
      <link>https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2021 17:01:02 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper&lt;/strong&gt;: BERT - Pre-training of Deep Bidirectional Transformers for Language Understanding&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Link&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aclweb.org/anthology/N19-1423.pdf&#34;&gt;https://bit.ly/3bdTUra&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: Jacob Devlin, Ming-Wei Chang, Kenton Lee, Kristina Toutanova&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Code&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/google-research/bert&#34;&gt;https://bit.ly/3vRXlM7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what&#34;&gt;What?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper proposes BERT which stands for Bidirectional Encoder Representations from Transformers. BERT is designed to pre-train deep bidirectional representations from unlabeled text. It performs a joint conditioning on both left and right context in all the layers. The pre-trained BERT model can be fine-tuned with one additional layer to create the final task-specific models i.e., without substantial task-specific architecture modifications. BERT achieves SOTA results on eleven NLP tasks such as natural language inference, question answering textual similarity, text classification, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The existing strategies for the pre-trained language representations are mostly based on unidirectional language models and hence are not very effective in capturing the entire context for sentence-level tasks. These are also harmful when applying fine-tuning based approaches to token-level tasks such as question answering, where it is crucial to capture context from both directions.
BERT aims to generate deep bidirectional representations by using maked language models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two main steps in the BERT framework are - pre-training and fine-tuning. Pre-training involves training the model on unlabeled data over different pretraining tasks. During fine-tuning, all the BERT parameters are fine-tuned using the labelled data from the downstream tasks. The fine-tuned model is different for each task, however, they share the same pre-trained parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;model-architecture&#34;&gt;Model Architecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying architecture of BERT is a multi-layer Transformer encoder, which is inherently bidirectional in nature. Two models are proposed in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BERT&lt;sub&gt;BASE&lt;/sub&gt; - 12 Transformer blocks, 12 self-attention heads, 768 is the hidden size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BERT&lt;sub&gt;LARGE&lt;/sub&gt; - 24 transformer blocks, 16 self-attention heads, 1024 is the hidden size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The model size of BERT&lt;sub&gt;BASE&lt;/sub&gt; and Open AI&amp;rsquo;s GPT was chosen to be the same.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/model.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/model.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;input-output-representations&#34;&gt;Input-Output Representations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BERT uses WordPiece embeddings with a 30,000 token vocabulary. The first token of every sequence is ([CLS]). The final hidden state corresponding to the [CLS] token is used as the aggregate sequence representation.&lt;br&gt;
To deal with sentence pairs, BERT uses a special token [SEP] to separate the two sentences. A learned embedding is added to every token indicating whether it is the first or the second sentence. The input embedding for each token is obtained by adding the corresponding token embedding (WordPiece embedding), segment embedding (first / second sentence) and position embedding (as in Transformers).&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/inputembeds.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/inputembeds.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bert-pre-training&#34;&gt;BERT pre-training&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BERT is pre-trained using two unsupervised tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;masked-lm&#34;&gt;Masked LM&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bidirectional model is more powerful than either a left-to-right model or the shallow concatenation of a left-to-right and right-to-left model.&lt;br&gt;
In order to train a deep bidirectional representation, some percentage (15% in the paper) of the input tokens are masked at random, and those masked tokens are predicted using an output softmax over the vocabulary. This is called a masked LM. The masking is performed by replacing the token with a [MASK] token. Now since the [MASK] token does not appear during fine-tuning, the [MASK] token is used 80% of the time. For 10% of the selected tokens (from the 15%) a random token is used to replace it and the token is kept unchanged for the rest 10%. The token is then predicted using cross-entropy loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;next-sentence-prediction-nsp&#34;&gt;Next Sentence Prediction (NSP)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand the relationship between two sentences (which is not captured by language modelling), a binarized NSP task is formulated. Here, when choosing the sentences A and B (refer to the model pre-training figure above) for each pre-training example, 50% of the time B is the actual next sentence and the rest 50% of the time, a random sentence from the corpus is used. The vector C (without fine-tuning) is used for NSP. This is helpful for tasks like Question Answering and Natural Language Inference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;pre-training-data&#34;&gt;Pre-training data&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is useful for BERT to use a document-level corpus rather than a shuffled sentence-level corpus. BERT 9as in the paper) uses the BookCorpus (800M words) and English Wikipedia (2500M words).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fine-tuning-bert&#34;&gt;Fine-tuning BERT&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of independently encoding text (sentence) pairs and then applying bidirectional cross attention, BERT uses the Transformer model architecture&amp;rsquo;s self-attention mechanism. Encoding the concatenated text (sentence) pair with self-attention effectively incorporates bidirectional cross attention between the two sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fine-tuning is performed for all the parameters and the task-specific inputs and outputs of the downstream task are plugged for fine-tuning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A and B are the sentence pairs in case of paraphrasing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A and B are hypothesis-premise pairs in the entailment task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A and B are question-passage pairs in question answering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A and B are the text and Φ in text classification or sequence tagging task&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the output, for the token-level tasks (sequence tagging, question answering), the token representations are fed into the output layer. For the sentence-level tasks, the representation of the [CLS] token is fed to the output layer for classification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;//downloads.mailchimp.com/js/signup-forms/popup/unique-methods/embed.js&#34; data-dojo-config=&#34;usePlainJson: true, isDebug: false&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;button style=&#34;background-color: #70ab17; color: #1770AB&#34; id=&#34;openpopup&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt; --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;button_cont&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;button id=&#34;openpopup&#34; class=&#34;example_a&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .example_a {
        color: #fff !important;
        text-transform: uppercase;
        text-decoration: none;
        background: #3f51b5;
        padding: 20px;
        border-radius: 5px;
        cursor: pointer;
        display: inline-block;
        border: none;
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }

    .example_a:hover {
        background: #434343;
        letter-spacing: 1px;
        -webkit-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        -moz-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        box-shadow: 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;

function showMailingPopUp() {
    window.dojoRequire([&#34;mojo/signup-forms/Loader&#34;], function(L) { L.start({&#34;baseUrl&#34;:&#34;mc.us4.list-manage.com&#34;,&#34;uuid&#34;:&#34;0b10ac14f50d7f4e7d11cf26a&#34;,&#34;lid&#34;:&#34;667a1bb3da&#34;,&#34;uniqueMethods&#34;:true}) })

    document.cookie = &#34;MCPopupClosed=;path=/;expires=Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 UTC&#34;;
}

document.getElementById(&#34;openpopup&#34;).onclick = function() {showMailingPopUp()};

&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GLUE&lt;/strong&gt; - The General Language Understanding Evaluation benchmark is a collection of a number of diverse NLP tasks. The 8 datasets the paper evaluates on, are shown below. For these tasks, the [CLS] representation (hidden vector associated with it) is used. The classification layer (a single layer is used) and its weights are the only new parameters introduced. Standard log softmax loss is used.
The model used a batch size of 32 and was fine-tuned for 3 epochs. The learning rate was chosen from a list based on performance on the validation set.
BERT&lt;sub&gt;LARGE&lt;/sub&gt; was unstable on small datasets so random restarts were done with data shuffling and classification layer initialization. It was found that BERT&lt;sub&gt;LARGE&lt;/sub&gt; significantly outperforms BERT&lt;sub&gt;BASE&lt;/sub&gt; (and all other models) across all tasks, especially those with very little training data.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/glue.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/glue.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQuAD v1.1&lt;/strong&gt; - A collection of 100k question-answer pairs. Given a question and a passage, the task is to predict the answer span in the text. The question and the passage are represented using A and B embedding respectively. A start vector S and end vector E is introduced in the output. The probability of token &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; being the start of the answer is given as&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/start.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/start.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and similarly for the end token. The score of a candidate span from position &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; to position &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt; is decided to be -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/etend.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/etend.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This objective is maximised to get the answer range. 
Batch size of 32, learning rate of 5e-5 was used and the model was fine-tuned for 3 epochs. 
Also, for enhanced performance, a prior fine-tuning on the Trivia-QA dataset was done before the fine-tuning on SQuAD.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad1.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad1.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQuAD v2.0&lt;/strong&gt; - This task allows for the possibility of no short answer existing in the passage for the question, to present a more realistic situation. So, in this case, for the questions which don&amp;rsquo;t have an answer, the start and end is set to be the [CLS] token. So, now there is also a s&lt;sub&gt;null&lt;/sub&gt; = S•C + E•C as the no-answer span score. 
For a non-null answer, a s&lt;sub&gt;i,j&lt;/sub&gt; = S•T&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; + E•T&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; is defined. A non-null answer is predicted when s&lt;sub&gt;i,j&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt; s&lt;sub&gt;null&lt;/sub&gt; + τ. τ is decided on the basis of the performance of the model on the validation set. TriviaQA data was not used for this model. The model was fine-tuned for 2 epochs with a learning rate of 5e-5 and a batch size of 48.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad2.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad2.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SWAG&lt;/strong&gt; - The Situations With Adversarial Generations (SWAG) dataset contains 113k sentence-pair completion examples that evaluate grounded commonsense inference. Given a sentence, the task is to choose the most correct continuation of the sentence among four choices. Scoring is performed for the four sentence pairs, the given sentence A and the possible continuation B. Here a vector is introduced whose dot product with the [CLS] token representation C denotes the score for each of the four choices and a softmax layer is used to get the probability distribution. The model was fine-tuned for 3 epochs with a learning rate of 2e-5 and a batch size of 16.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/swag.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/swag.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the analysis/ablation studies section -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two additional modes of pre-training were performed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No NSP&lt;/strong&gt; - The model is pre-trained with mask LM but not with the NSP task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LTR and No NSP&lt;/strong&gt; - Instead of a masked LM, a standard left-to-right LM is used and the NSP task is again not performed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LTR model performs worse than the MLM model on all tasks, with large drops on MRPC and SQuAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An LTR model performs poorly on token predictions and hence doesn&amp;rsquo;t perform well on SQuAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For strengthening the LTR models, a randomly initialized BiLSTM model is added on the top. This improves the results on SQuAD but does not perform well on the GLUE tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separately training LTR (left-to-right) and RTL (right-to-left) models and concatenating them for the token representations is an approach similar to ELMo. But the authors mention that this is twice as expensive as a single bidirectional model. Also, this is unintuitive for tasks like Question Answering since the RTL model would not be able to condition the answer on the question. Furthermore, it is less powerful than a deep bidirectional model, since it can use both left and right context at every layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation1.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation1.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BERT&lt;sub&gt;BASE&lt;/sub&gt; contains 110M parameters and BERT&lt;sub&gt;LARGE&lt;/sub&gt; contains 340M parameters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger models lead to a strict accuracy improvement across all four datasets, even for MRPC (paraphrasing) which only has 3,600 labelled training examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BERT claims to be the first model to demonstrate convincingly
that scaling to extreme model sizes also leads to large improvements on very small scale tasks, provided that the model has been sufficiently pre-trained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the model is fine-tuned directly on the downstream task and uses only a very small number of randomly initialized additional parameters, the task-specific models can benefit from the larger, more expressive pre-trained representations even when downstream task data is very small.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation2.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation2.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feature-based model, in which fixed features are obtained from the model, has some advantages. Firstly, not all tasks can be modelled using a Transformer encoder and require task-specific model architecture to be added.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secondly, pre-computing the expensive representations and using them for multiple experiments with cheaper models is a computational benefit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The authors compare the feature-based approach for the BERT inference and the normal BERT for the NER task. In the inference part of the feature-based approach, the activations from one or more layers are taken &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; any fine-tuning of the BERT parameters for the NER task. These contextual embeddings are used as input to a randomly initialized two-layer 768-dimensional BiLSTM before the classification layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although this does not perform better than the fine-tuned approach, the best performing method used the concatenation of the last four hidden layers&amp;rsquo; representation of the pre-trained Transformer as the token representation is only 0.3 F1 behind the fine-tuning approach. So, the authors conclude that BERT is effective for both fine-tuning and feature-based approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation3.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation3.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;//downloads.mailchimp.com/js/signup-forms/popup/unique-methods/embed.js&#34; data-dojo-config=&#34;usePlainJson: true, isDebug: false&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;button style=&#34;background-color: #70ab17; color: #1770AB&#34; id=&#34;openpopup&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt; --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;button_cont&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;button id=&#34;openpopup&#34; class=&#34;example_a&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .example_a {
        color: #fff !important;
        text-transform: uppercase;
        text-decoration: none;
        background: #3f51b5;
        padding: 20px;
        border-radius: 5px;
        cursor: pointer;
        display: inline-block;
        border: none;
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }

    .example_a:hover {
        background: #434343;
        letter-spacing: 1px;
        -webkit-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        -moz-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        box-shadow: 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;

function showMailingPopUp() {
    window.dojoRequire([&#34;mojo/signup-forms/Loader&#34;], function(L) { L.start({&#34;baseUrl&#34;:&#34;mc.us4.list-manage.com&#34;,&#34;uuid&#34;:&#34;0b10ac14f50d7f4e7d11cf26a&#34;,&#34;lid&#34;:&#34;667a1bb3da&#34;,&#34;uniqueMethods&#34;:true}) })

    document.cookie = &#34;MCPopupClosed=;path=/;expires=Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 UTC&#34;;
}

document.getElementById(&#34;openpopup&#34;).onclick = function() {showMailingPopUp()};

&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GLUE&lt;/strong&gt; - The General Language Understanding Evaluation benchamrk is a collection of a number of diverse NLP tasks. The 8 datasets the paper evaluates on, are shown below. For these tasks, the [CLS] representation (hidden vector associated with it) is used. The classification layer (a single layer is used) and its weights are the only new parameters introduced. Standard log softmax loss is used.
Model used batch size of 32 and was fine tuned for 3 epochs. Learning rate was chosen from a list based on performance on validation set.
BERT&lt;sub&gt;LARGE&lt;/sub&gt; was unstable on small datasets so random restarts were done with data shuffling and classification layer initialization. It was found that BERT&lt;sub&gt;LARGE&lt;/sub&gt; significantly outperforms BERT&lt;sub&gt;BASE&lt;/sub&gt; (and all other models) across all tasks, especially those with very little training data.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/glue.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/glue.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQuAD v1.1&lt;/strong&gt; - A collection of 100k question-answer pairs. Given a question and a passage, the task is to predict the answer span in the text. The question and the passage are represneted using A and B embedding respectively. A start vector S and end vector E is introduced in the output. The probability of token &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; being the start of the answer is given as&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/start.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/start.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and similarly for the end token. The score of a candidate span form position &lt;em&gt;i&lt;/em&gt; to position &lt;em&gt;j&lt;/em&gt; is decided to be -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/etend.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/etend.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This objective is maximised to get the answer range. 
Batch size of 32, learning rate of 5e-5 was used and the model was fine-tuned for 3 epochs. 
Also, for enhanced performance, a prior fine-tunig on the Trivia-QA dataset was done before the fine-tuning on SQuAD.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad1.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad1.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQuAD v2.0&lt;/strong&gt; - Thsi task allows for the possibilty of no short answer existing in the passage for the question, to present a more realistic situation. So, in this case, for the questions which don&amp;rsquo;t have a answer, the start and end is set to be the [CLS] token. So, now there is also a s&lt;sub&gt;null&lt;/sub&gt; = S•C + E•C as the no-answer span score. 
For a non-null answer, a s&lt;sub&gt;i,j&lt;/sub&gt; = S•T&lt;sub&gt;i&lt;/sub&gt; + E•T&lt;sub&gt;j&lt;/sub&gt; is defined. A non-null answer is predicted when s&lt;sub&gt;i,j&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;gt; s&lt;sub&gt;null&lt;/sub&gt; + τ. τ is decided on the basis of the performance of the model on the validation set. TriviaQA data was not used for this model. The model was fine-tuned for 2 epochs with a learning rate of 5e-5 and a batch size of 48.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad2.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/squad2.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SWAG&lt;/strong&gt; - The Situations With Adversarial Generations (SWAG) dataset contains 113k sentence-pair completion examples that evaluate grounded commonsense inference. Given a sentence, the task is to choose the most correct continuation of the sentence among four choices. A scoring is performed for the four sentence pairs, the given sentence A and the possible continuation B. Here a vector is introduiced whose dot product with the [CLS] token representation C denotes the score for each of the four choices and a softmax layer is used to get the probabilty distribution. The model was fine-tuned for 3 epochs with a learning rate of 2e-5 and a batch size of 16.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/swag.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/swag.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the analysis/ablation studies section -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two additional modes of pre-training were performed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No NSP&lt;/strong&gt; - The model is pre-trained with mask LM but not with the NSP task.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LTR and No NSP&lt;/strong&gt; - Instead of a masked LM, a standard left-to-right LM is used and the NSP task is again not performed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LTR model performs worse than the MLM model on all tasks, with large drops on MRPC and SQuAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An LTR model perofrms poorly on token predictions, and hence doesn&amp;rsquo;t perform well on SQuAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For strengthening the LTR models, a randomly initialized BiLSTM model is added on the top. This improves the results on SQuAD but does not perform well on the GLUE tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separately training LTR (left-to-right) and RTL (right-to-left) models and concatenating them for the token representations is an approach similar to ELMo. But the authors mention that this is twice as expensive as a single bidirectional model. Also, this is unintuitve for tasks like Question Answering since the RTL model would not be able to condition the answer on the question. Furthermore, it is less powerful than a deep bidirectional model, since it can use both left and right context at every layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation1.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation1.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BERT&lt;sub&gt;BASE&lt;/sub&gt; contains 110M parameters and BERT&lt;sub&gt;LARGE&lt;/sub&gt; contains 340M parameters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Larger models lead to a strict accuracy improvement across all four datasets, even for MRPC (paraphrasing) which only has 3,600 labeled training examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;BERT claims to be the first model to demonstrate convincingly
that scaling to extreme model sizes also leads to large improvements on very small scale tasks, provided that the model has been sufficiently pre-trained.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When the model is fine-tuned directly on the downstream task and uses only a very small number of randomly initialized additional parameters,the task specific models can benefit from the larger, more expressive pre-trained representations even when downstream task data is very small.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation2.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation2.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The feature based model, in which fixed features are obtainned from the model, has some advantages. Firstly, not all tasks can be modeled using a Transformer encoder and require task-specific model architecture to be added.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secondly, pre-computing the expensive representations and using them for multiple experiments with cheaper models is a computational benefit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The authors compare the feature-based approach for the BERT inference and the normal BERT for the NER task. In the inference part of the feature-based aapproach the activations from one or more layers are taken &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; any fine-tuning of the BERT paramaetrs for the NER task. These contextual embeddings are used as input to a randomly initialized a two-layer 768-dimensional BiLSTM before the classification layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although this does not perform better than the the fine-tuned approach, but the best performing method which used the concatenation of the last four hidden layers&amp;rsquo; representaion of the pre-trained Transformer as the token represnetation is only 0.3 F1 behind the fine-tuning approach. So, the authors conclude that BERT is effective for both fine-tunign and feature-based approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation3.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-09_pretraining_deep_bidirectional_transformers_bert/images/ablation3.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have also released an annotated version of the paper. If you are interested, you can find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shreyansh26/Annotated-ML-Papers/blob/main/BERT.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all for now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;//downloads.mailchimp.com/js/signup-forms/popup/unique-methods/embed.js&#34; data-dojo-config=&#34;usePlainJson: true, isDebug: false&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;button style=&#34;background-color: #70ab17; color: #1770AB&#34; id=&#34;openpopup&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt; --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;button_cont&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;button id=&#34;openpopup&#34; class=&#34;example_a&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .example_a {
        color: #fff !important;
        text-transform: uppercase;
        text-decoration: none;
        background: #3f51b5;
        padding: 20px;
        border-radius: 5px;
        cursor: pointer;
        display: inline-block;
        border: none;
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }

    .example_a:hover {
        background: #434343;
        letter-spacing: 1px;
        -webkit-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        -moz-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        box-shadow: 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;

function showMailingPopUp() {
    window.dojoRequire([&#34;mojo/signup-forms/Loader&#34;], function(L) { L.start({&#34;baseUrl&#34;:&#34;mc.us4.list-manage.com&#34;,&#34;uuid&#34;:&#34;0b10ac14f50d7f4e7d11cf26a&#34;,&#34;lid&#34;:&#34;667a1bb3da&#34;,&#34;uniqueMethods&#34;:true}) })

    document.cookie = &#34;MCPopupClosed=;path=/;expires=Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 UTC&#34;;
}

document.getElementById(&#34;openpopup&#34;).onclick = function() {showMailingPopUp()};

&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script data-name=&#34;BMC-Widget&#34; data-cfasync=&#34;false&#34; src=&#34;https://cdnjs.buymeacoffee.com/1.0.0/widget.prod.min.js&#34; data-id=&#34;shreyanshsingh&#34; data-description=&#34;Support me on Buy me a coffee!&#34; data-message=&#34;&#34; data-color=&#34;#FF5F5F&#34; data-position=&#34;Right&#34; data-x_margin=&#34;18&#34; data-y_margin=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/shreyansh_26&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shreyansh26&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; or connect on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/shreyansh26/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper Summary #3 - Improving Language Understanding by Generative Pre-Training</title>
      <link>https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2021 13:42:14 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper&lt;/strong&gt;: Improving Language Understanding by Generative Pre-Training&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Link&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/openai-assets/research-covers/language-unsupervised/language_understanding_paper.pdf&#34;&gt;https://bit.ly/3xITvGP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Blog&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://openai.com/blog/language-unsupervised/&#34;&gt;https://openai.com/blog/language-unsupervised/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt;: Alec Radford, Karthik Narasimhan, Tim Salimans, Ilya Sutskever&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Code&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/openai/finetune-transformer-lm&#34;&gt;https://bit.ly/3gUFrUX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what&#34;&gt;What?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper proposes a semi-supervised technique that shows better performance on a wide variety of tasks like textual entailment, question answering, semantic similarity text classification by using a single task-agnostic model. The model can overcome the constraints of the small amount of annotated data for these specific tasks by performing an unsupervised generative-pretraining of a language model on a large diverse text corpus followed by supervised discriminative fine-tuning on each specific task. The pretraining model remains the same for all the tasks. Only a small, task-aware input adaptation is required when performing the fine-tuning. The model significantly improved the state-of-the-art (at the time) in 9 of the 12 tasks studied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most deep learning models require a substantial amount of data, which makes them difficult to train for tasks in which there is a dearth of good quality annotated data. Historically, pre-trained word embeddings have been used for such cases but the word-level information in itself is sometimes not enough for many of the complex tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of the model is to learn a universal representation that transfers with little adaptation to a wide range of tasks. The paper assumes access to a large corpus of unlabeled text and several datasets with manually annotated training examples (the target tasks). The unlabeled corpus and the annotated datasets need not be in the same domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A two-stage training procedure is used. First, a language modelling (LM) objective is used on the unlabeled data to learn the initial parameters of the model. Next, these parameters are adapted to a target task using the corresponding supervised objective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Transformer (specifically a Transfomer decoder) is used as the underlying architecture. Transformers work better than LSTMs (shown in the results as well) because they can capture long-term dependencies well which results in robust transfer performance across diverse tasks.  Furthermore, during the transfer, as mentioned above, task-specific input adaptations are used which process the structured text input as a single contiguous sequence of tokens. This is something very interesting and will be shown in the subsequent sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;unsupervised-pre-training&#34;&gt;Unsupervised pre-training&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A standard forward LM objective is used to maximise the likelihood -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/unsupervised-lm.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/unsupervised-lm.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, , &lt;em&gt;U&lt;/em&gt; is the corpus of tokens {&lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;,&amp;hellip; &lt;em&gt;u&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;}, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; is the context window size and the conditional probability &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;  is modeled using a network with parameters Θ. SGD is used to learn the parameters. The model uses a multi-layer Transformer decoder. The multi-head self-attention is applied over the input context tokens. This is followed by position-wise feedforward layers to produce an output probability distribution over the target tokens.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/probcalc.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/probcalc.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;em&gt;U&lt;/em&gt; is (u&lt;sub&gt;-k&lt;/sub&gt;,&amp;hellip;, u&lt;sub&gt;-1&lt;/sub&gt;) which is the context vector of tokens, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is the number of layers, &lt;em&gt;W&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;e&lt;/sub&gt; is the token embedding matrix and &lt;em&gt;W&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;p&lt;/sub&gt; is the position embedding matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;supervised-fine-tuning&#34;&gt;Supervised fine-tuning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the training of the model with optimization &lt;em&gt;L&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;, the parameters are now adapted to the supervised target task. The labelled dataset is denoted by &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt;, where each instance is a sequence of input tokens, &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;,&amp;hellip;,&lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;, along with a label &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;. The inputs are passed through the pre-trained model to obtain the final transformer block&amp;rsquo;s activation &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;l&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;, which is then fed into an added linear output layer with parameters &lt;em&gt;W&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;y&lt;/sub&gt; to predict &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/fintune1.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/fintune1.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective to be maximized is as follows&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/fintune2.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/fintune2.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using an LM objective as an auxiliary objective to the finetuning helped to improve the generalization of the supervised model and make it converge faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall objective can be written as -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/objective-fin.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/objective-fin.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;task-specific-input-transformations&#34;&gt;Task-specific input transformations&lt;/h3&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/input-transform.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/input-transform.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the pretrained model is trained on a contiguous sequence of texts, to handle the inputs of the various tasks, certain input transformations are needed as shown above. These transformations help to avoid making extensive changes to the architecture across tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Textual Entailment&lt;/strong&gt; - The premise (&lt;em&gt;p&lt;/em&gt;) and the hypothesis (&lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;) sequences are concatenated with a delimiter token in between.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Similarity&lt;/strong&gt; - Since there is no inherent ordering of the two sequences being compared, the input sequence is modified to contain both possible sentence orderings (with a delimiter in between). Each of these concatenated sequences is processed independently to produce two sequence representations &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;l&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt; which are then element-wise added before feeding to the linear output layer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question Answering&lt;/strong&gt; - This one is interesting. For a given context document &lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;, question &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt; and a set of possible answers {&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;}. The document and question are concatenated with each of the possible answers, with a delimiter token in between [&lt;em&gt;z&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;q&lt;/em&gt;;$;&lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sub&gt;k&lt;/sub&gt;]. Each of these sequences is processed independently by the model and then normalized by a softmax layer to produce an output distribution over possible answers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The model specifications for the experimental setup are shown below -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/setup.PNG&#34; data-caption=&#34;Experimental Setup&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/setup.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Experimental Setup
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The datasets that were used are listed below -&lt;/p&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/datasets.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/datasets.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural Language Inference&lt;/strong&gt; - This task is challenging due to the presence of a wide variety of phenomena like lexical entailment, coreference, and lexical and syntactic ambiguity. The model performs better than the state-of-the-art in 4 (MNLI, QNLI, SNLI, SciTail) out of 5 datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/nli.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/nli.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question Answering and Commonsense Reasoning&lt;/strong&gt; - The RACE dataset (passages with associated questions from middle and high school exams) and Story Cloze dataset (selecting correct ending to multi-sentence stories from two options) were used. The model outperformed the baseline on both these datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/qa.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/qa.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Semantic Similarity&lt;/strong&gt; - The challenges in this task are recognizing rephrasing, negation, and handling ambiguity. The model performs better on 2 (QQP and STS-B) of the 3 datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Classification&lt;/strong&gt; - The model performs better on both Corpus of Linguistic Accepttability (CoLA) dataset and is at par with the state-of-the-art results on the Stanford Sentiment Treebank dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/classification.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/classification.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key points from the analysis section -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More the number of layers that are transferred from the pretrained model to the supervised target task, the better is the performance on the target tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To understand whether the unsupervised pre-training is effective or not, zero-shot testing was also performed i.e., using the pre-trained model directly without any finetuning. The model performance is stable and steadily increases over training suggesting that the generative pre-training supports the learning of a wide variety of task-relevant functionality. LSTMs exhibit higher variance in their zero-shot performance.
The testing and input transformations for using the pretrained model directly are explained below -













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/zeroshot.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/zeroshot.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;













&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/trend.PNG&#34; &gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://shreyansh26.github.io/post/2021-05-02_language_understanding_generative_pretraining/images/trend.PNG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; &gt;&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the ablation studies, the authors show that the auxiliary LM objective helps on the NLI tasks and QQP (Quora Question Pairs data).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overall, larger datasets benefit from the auxiliary objective more than the smaller datasets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In general, the Transformer architecture performs better than a 2048 unit single layer LSTM model (if the Transformer in the pretraining model is replaced by an LSTM) on all datasets except the MRPC (Microsoft Paraphrase Corpus for semantic similarity) dataset.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On comparing this model with the same transformer architecture trained in a supervised manner, it is observed that the model with pre-training performs better. This consistent for all the tasks mentioned in the paper, suggesting that pre-training helps to capture important linguistic information which is not captured when training with a supervised approach alone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have also released an annotated version of the paper. If you are interested, you can find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shreyansh26/Annotated-ML-Papers/blob/main/GPT1.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all for now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;//downloads.mailchimp.com/js/signup-forms/popup/unique-methods/embed.js&#34; data-dojo-config=&#34;usePlainJson: true, isDebug: false&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;!-- &lt;button style=&#34;background-color: #70ab17; color: #1770AB&#34; id=&#34;openpopup&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt; --&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;button_cont&#34; align=&#34;center&#34;&gt;&lt;button id=&#34;openpopup&#34; class=&#34;example_a&#34;&gt;Subscribe to my posts!&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
    .example_a {
        color: #fff !important;
        text-transform: uppercase;
        text-decoration: none;
        background: #3f51b5;
        padding: 20px;
        border-radius: 5px;
        cursor: pointer;
        display: inline-block;
        border: none;
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }

    .example_a:hover {
        background: #434343;
        letter-spacing: 1px;
        -webkit-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        -moz-box-shadow: 0px 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        box-shadow: 5px 40px -10px rgba(0,0,0,0.57);
        transition: all 0.4s ease 0s;
    }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;

function showMailingPopUp() {
    window.dojoRequire([&#34;mojo/signup-forms/Loader&#34;], function(L) { L.start({&#34;baseUrl&#34;:&#34;mc.us4.list-manage.com&#34;,&#34;uuid&#34;:&#34;0b10ac14f50d7f4e7d11cf26a&#34;,&#34;lid&#34;:&#34;667a1bb3da&#34;,&#34;uniqueMethods&#34;:true}) })

    document.cookie = &#34;MCPopupClosed=;path=/;expires=Thu, 01 Jan 1970 00:00:00 UTC&#34;;
}

document.getElementById(&#34;openpopup&#34;).onclick = function() {showMailingPopUp()};

&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script data-name=&#34;BMC-Widget&#34; data-cfasync=&#34;false&#34; src=&#34;https://cdnjs.buymeacoffee.com/1.0.0/widget.prod.min.js&#34; data-id=&#34;shreyanshsingh&#34; data-description=&#34;Support me on Buy me a coffee!&#34; data-message=&#34;&#34; data-color=&#34;#FF5F5F&#34; data-position=&#34;Right&#34; data-x_margin=&#34;18&#34; data-y_margin=&#34;18&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow me on &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/shreyansh_26&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/shreyansh26&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; or connect on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/shreyansh26/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
